all right it's December 26 2024 this is
Daniel Friedman it's active infrance
stream
9.1 how to accelerate active inference
Mountain car in RX INF fur.
JL and hope everyone is having a good
End ofe season looking forward to
different updates different live chats
see what happens along the way I'll
start the stream off with making a
GitHub
push all right while that's happening
I'm going to head over into cursor this
is what we're going to be exploring
covering today which is modifying an RX
and fur package example made by the
developers and moving it from a notebook
format into a script format adding some
more visualizations and analyses and
then doing uh setup script hopefully to
make it easier to get it going on your
computer and meta analysis and right now
there's a big meta analysis happening
but we'll look at some past runs that
finished just a few seconds ago okay
so check the
GitHub this is uh B based on
the current
version
3.8 of reactive Bas RX inf.
JL and
just to keep
it separate and clear made a fork or a
branch from the exact version today and
then put all of the work that I'm about
to go into into this examples folder SL
Mountain car so it's
a
branch on RX and fjl and in the video
description are all the links
okay so GitHub push for now to start
another Standalone and meta
analysis so here's where I've gotten to
after many speed bumps and and fun along
the way this is incursor right click
open an integrated
terminal first if you
haven't run script Julia setup.
JL probably also other settings will
need to be bumped up against on
different settings uh also I brought it
up synced it to the current version um
just after after building part of it so
there's probably a lot of inefficiencies
it's of course Very cursor SL
clawes so there could be a lot of
redundancy a lot of ways to
go um but I'm going to run the setup
script then we'll look at the Standalone
and The Meta
analysis okay so this is as as mentioned
branches off of the RX and
fur example active inference Mountain C
okay let's just briefly look at
setup see what's happening while it's
finishing
this there could probably a lot of
sorting of of this um different packages
are
installed the RX and fur Keystone
package is installed from the local
GitHub repo so probably it would take
some other different way to export
functions in a different way um calls
probably some set of automatic
dependency
installations uh
pre-existing explicit calls that I uh
typed in like most recently this stats
plots so definitely figure out what else
could be changed to get this working on
your own computer but at the end I hope
it accurately says yes RX infers
functional some of the core packages
that we need are loaded here's the Julia
version project path RX infer path and
then how to run the
scripts and and that can be probably
developed okay so that's the
setup then there's the
Standalone Julia
Mountain
car Standalone this one has today's date
and a file
name just to give it a static version as
as a single file
snapshot but the meta analysis is much
more scattered across methods
scripts so the single Mountain car stand
alone has the date Okay so
let's look before we go into the code at
how they set up and characterize the
mountain car
problem okay and so it's written in this
sort of notebook blog post multimedia
style active inference Mountain car this
is from the RX and for JL documentation
a group of friends is going to a camping
site that is located on the biggest
mountain in the Netherlands they use an
electric car for the trip when they are
almost there the car's battery is almost
empty and is therefore limiting the
engine Force Unfortunately they are in
the middle of a valley and don't have
enough power to reach the camping site
night is
falling and they still need to reach the
top of the mountain as Rescuers let us
develop an active inference AI agent
that can get them up the hill with
limited engine
power
okay before we go into the technical
details here's just a single perplexity
prompt give an overview of the mountain
car problem from control theory at four
level SL types of depth plain archetypal
Ultra Technical and esoteric and also
generated some images so we can generate
some more images now or people can
suggest other
prompt so plain understanding the
problem involves an underpowered car
stuck in a valley between two Hills the
car's engine is too weak to climb
directly up to the right Hill to reach a
goal flat instead it must swing back and
forth building up momentum by driving up
the opposite Hill first until it gains
enough energy to reach the
target archetypal perspective this
scenario exemplifies the fundamental
principle that direct paths aren't
always optimal the car must first move
away from its goal driving left to
ultimately reach it on the right a
counterintuitive strategy that
demonstrates how complex systems often
require indirect act approaches the
problem has become a classic test
case for reinforcement learning
algorithms because it requires learning
this nonobvious
solution so the active inference
approach that RX Ander is going to
implement doesn't have a trained reward
or proposed reward function on some data
set of successful or not successful
traces it's going to be directly from
the distributions okay technical
analysis we'll see in more
specifics getting into the scripts and
then I'll be the last one esoteric
implications the mountain car problem
transcends its mechanical nature to
represent a metaphor for optimization in
complex Landscapes the system
demonstrates the necessity of building
potential energy through oscillatory
Behavior the interplay between kinetic
and potential energy transformations the
emergence of sophisticated behavior from
simple physical rules the relationship
between local Optima Valley and Global
Optima goal the problems enduring
relevance stems from its ability to
challenge both traditional control
methods and modern machine learning
approaches while maintaining
mathematical elegance and its
Simplicity
okay so the goal for this stream and
then we'll look more at the specifics of
the mountain car and the code itself to
learn about RX and fur hopefully
correctly or at least helpfully
implement
one useful experiment to learn about
Julia and all these different
tools and shout out to Andrew for the
early Julia adoption and and
insights um here is using cursor 44.8 RX
andur 3.8 or
two Julia 1.11.2 and then for the llm in
cursor Claude 3.5
Sonet 2024 10 22 all
right here's the finished single
Standalone that we ran started during
the
stream it is going to implement two
different simulations with the same
physics and two different approaches to
strategy first is going to be the naive
approach which always pushes to the
right and then the second is going to be
this active inference approach with a
given look ahead period and this script
goes into the
outputs so here's the new one in green
here are the outputs of the single
simulation and this will give an
intuition for what the single um
Standalone does so first comparison dog
GI so here the single parameter
combination that is
used was chosen it's I think similar
proportional or the same to what was
used in the original example
notebook and there's two different dots
representing the cars position
simulation on this landscape and we'll
look at how physics is given on this
landscape so the rules of physics are
specified and the
elevation and the potential and the
kinetic energies are calculated in a
sort of basic physics simulation style
not
simply uh modifying some attribute of
the direct landscape function
itself and they both start at .5 and
they're both trying to get to positive
point5 the colors will change I think
throughout but naive control is red and
it drives right and it oscillates a
little bit but reaches a fixed point
where the friction and the
gravity are equivalent to the engine's
limiting force and that reaches this
staple point the blue active inference
agent has this
anticipatory simulated trace and I think
it's it's definitely worthy of
another long investigation or how does
it how does it distributionally fit this
policy
anticipation and what is the
computational complexity as we scale the
time Horizon of inference but we can see
that with this preference for being
higher up the active inference agent can
see that it can get higher up to the
left than it is on the right by moving
that
way and that from uh already being up on
the right slope and oscillate its way to
the goal position and you can imagine
that that there's going to be um
combinations of physics and engine force
and goal position that are easily or
impossible to
attain right going through the rest of
the images in this single case um output
but first going to start the well let's
just go through all these first okay so
this is the action distribution the
naive control has is always picking that
one value to go right with one whereas
the octave inference
now it's in tan it or red has at least I
don't know if I'm perfectly implementing
what the notebook does but at least it
does have some policy variance and it
one that for this parameter combination
does get it up to the goal action
comparison so there's another way to
look at that this is the knife control
with now in blue with the yal 1
policy function
output active
inference agent having
this more back and forth control policy
swinging between two and -2 I'm not sure
what this if this is scaled to a
different
number it's but none of this is meant to
say that this is the best fit it's
really just a first step towards
figuring out what what kinds of tools
and interfaces for generative models and
for RX and fur can we use to start doing
some useful parameter sweeps across
different regions of of parameter space
and structure models okay these are
State action
Maps so here's position on the x-axis
velocity on the Y AIS for
um there's another one that makes sense
yeah so here's here's the trace of the
naive n blue and active
inference showing these different
trajectories they start out with zero
velocity at
.5 here's a version where the vectors
are
added the naive
control follows this blue spiral to its
fix Point
attractor the active inference agent has
this oscillatory Behavior reflected with
a loop not just a spiral that ends up
reaching a higher net position via
increased velocity which is what it
needs to get up the
hill here's the predictive element of
the active inference agent here's
velocity
distribution there's a wider
range of velocities ranging from the the
negative to the positive positive
further in the active inference
agent um energy comparison this is not
like variational free energy this is the
kinetic minus the potential or kinetic
and the potential energy
so we can look at this calculation
though and Energy Efficiency I think is
the integral or something of this but oh
not exactly sure okay so this state
action map is showing that trajectory
and then mapping overlay with which
action was
taken so starting here 2.0 was used
that's moving to the right and then
abruptly the policy switches to
-2.0 then policy switches here
and
then the position is um
approached and I I think that's an
interesting question like to what extent
does it have inertia to meet the
goal or does it engage in a sort of
zenos paradox slowing down as it
converges if it has the engine control
so it has to be kind of like a run past
the Finish Line situation at least in
terms of the explicit preference
distribution otherwise you you get sort
of slowing Behavior leading up to the go
I don't know that could just be a total
artifact of this
hill okay that's
the that's the uh
single Standalone
output okay now config do
is going to
specify a metaanalysis
sweep so here's what what it's going to
look like here it was 200 simulations so
times definitely interesting to profile
how much is the startup time for one app
model and
then how what is there any other further
caching because starting the first one
seems to take longer at has the sort of
RX and firm Machinery comes online I
guess but we we'll look at the code viz
too it should be interesting um and and
again it's all just initial takes for
hopefully people and others to improve
on it so here's the config
dot metaanalysis so there's two knobs in
this parameter grid sweep the force
limit of the engine and the friction
coefficient of the landscape the gravity
constant is kept
constant for each of the engine force
and the friction coefficient you give a
minimum and a maximum so I think the one
that just ran maybe it was this one I
don't
know
oh let's see
[Music]
77 we'll just run a clean
so minimum and maximum force and
friction let's do a higher
resolution 1 to
[Music]
27 01 to
27 so this is going to do 15 * 15
multiplied by the number of episodes per
parameter combination so that can be
used for technical replicates
so then that parameter combination we
can understand the variance profile of
it too I'll I'll set that to
two maximum steps per
episode let's leave it at 100 planning
Horizon leave it at
40 initial
position this is also not position and
velocity third would be acceleration etc
etc etc snap crackle pop all that um div
grad
curl Target state is the position and
velocity preferences so I think again
interesting to see are those convergent
or does Nera
carry some plotting here kind of as an
experiment kind of as a bit of a um
local coding
Optima uh some of the plots are are in
in asky plain text and then some output
so 155 so that
was just to sort of recap run setup. JL
confirm that RX infer works then
run just the stand
alone Mountain car Standalone
12264 and that will do the
simulation we did that close that
window this is another thing
alone now clearing now we're going to
run the Met
analysis so hopefully this will
work meanwhile let us explore the code
VI
briefly
visualization so not sure if this is
accurate this is uh TBD with RX infer
experts but here the prompt for
this um graphical visualization
was I'll I'll modify the prompt just so
we have three free flows left for this
out of five here's the meta
analysis let's close that one meta
analysis plugging away on the terminal
we'll see if it has to be D or rebug and
then we'll do a graph V free version on
the free on this flow
visualization emphasize the component of
active inference and the free
energy princip
okay looks like we passed the first
phase so this loaded the configuration
Tomo set up the parameter
batch objects plus methods so now we'll
see how the simulations go um the
first part I think takes longer and then
the second it hits a second rate I'm not
sure which I think might maybe does the
the active inference ones then all the
naive and the the so we we'll see how
long it takes to click to
% and then see how long it takes to
finish okay
meanwhile here was the graph
this so the The Prompt
was and again I I I hope slash don't
know this is accurate
would be really interested to explore
how we could develop these methods and
get
some
um stable versioning if these are
accurate and uh use them for learning RX
invert so Trace how a probabilistic
model specification transforms
transforms from App model macro
definition through node creation it's to
final compiled graph structure including
node contraction optimization
emphasize the component of active
inference and the free energy principle
not sure that matter so here
is ostensibly looking through parts of
this package not sure how much of a
rocket and all these other pieces are in
there but you
know here's some references in the code
again I'm working in the RX infer
Branch so here it does find a place in
the
documents so the app model
macro is passed to graph PPL
package here's a section this is kind of
like using cursor SL Cod VI as a rag for
code and docs facilitated because the RX
infer
documentation is is on their GitHub as
well so
then let's
see app model macro definition uses
graph PPL and that gets customized by
reactive message passing graph PPL back
end okay
maybe transformation
pipeline compos simple operators folds
mathematical expressions and adds
brackets to ensure correct argument
handling so the app
model
parameters and syntax get kind of
unpacked inject Tilda right hand side
aliases
that creates nodes and variables based
on model
specification from the
nodes so this is the
statistical base graph I guess
interesting although some nodes in RX
INF fur. JL already come with their own
meta structure users have the
flexibility to Define different meta
structures for those nodes and also for
custom
ones a meta structure is created by
using the struct statement in
Julia okay that is converted to a factor
graph that's sort of
the post 2017 is work with bird def rise
friston
par here's the free energy
[Music]
optimization
component okay so the factor graph
construction I guess whether in the
scheduled
forny classic non-reactive style
or ostensibly but not necessarily in the
RX infer reactive message passing
setting probably the message passing can
be scheduled or reactive
differently here's variational free
energy variational free energy then
defines a functional objective that
includes the model and a variational
distribution over the latent
variables not sure if this is going to
always be the case for any graph or how
how how that um comes to be for a given
Factor graph but these are just
questions to to learn from Explorer and
then here's a
specific bet free energy I know Dave
told me it was one way or the other but
probably I said the wrong one but the
Betha
approximation um okay meanwhile 21% done
with this 225 time
something um metaanalysis sweep
the BFE can be iteratively optimized for
each individual variational distribution
in turn optimization of the BFE is thus
more manageable than direct optimization
of the
vfe so they use also
these methods that that in the RX infer
group this year we we kind
of talk about as
the what are they
called the six
functions so they are a convention which
provides interpretability and
structuring for ARX Ander action
perception Loops by using a canonical
set of
methods so the and thanks to many of the
participants throughout this year in
getting the documentation doing all
these experiments
too so I I I I don't know how accurately
I've implemented it but here's what we
had and there's different ways to do it
the so in the
structured
scheduled single time step all every
node one time step Factor graph
Logistics um it's not reactive it's like
moving the whole simulation ahead
one
click the the I mean what I understand
of with the reactive message passing
situation is that it brings
some
computational reactive methods to the
local variant of a free energy the be
free
energy that enable variational inference
to be done in a in a flexible and
effective way
okay node
contraction oh the six function so once
into the reactive
setting whereas in the scheduled version
it was just iterate through this list of
of um
operations let's do div rise
this is graphical brain belief
propagation and active inference forist
and Par devise
2017 figure
one showing how one time step updating
of the
PDP graph up here translates to these
analytical updates occurring in this
scheduled order on this forny graph
which is a transformation of kind of
nodes into edges and vice versa between
the bay and the forny graph and there's
also recent other papers and live
streams and such but this 2017 is just
laying out the relationship between the
single time step of basy and
updating and the update rules that can
be scheduled on that for graph so then
reactive moved that
into a much more General situation where
different processes can be playing out
with different Logics and speeds so
there could be like One sensor at 100
htz and one at 1 Hertz and you're
neither sampling too much or too little
however then there's this question of
okay well we're going to specify the app
model using the RX and for app model
syntax
looking like
this
here's transition function modeling
transition due to gravity and friction
so updating position and velocity given
the
physics the the structure of affordance
or
policy in action
space um
inverse Engine Force not sure why it
needs to be defined
here this
is I I hope just putting out
some stabs and phone trails in into the
dark for people to
clarify perform techno invective make it
clearer make other
documentation all all these kinds of
things I'm I'm and I'm I'm not sure if
I've completely perfectly mapped it into
the script form but from this example
this is the proper reference
version the app model function for the
agent type like Mountain car is defined
like in this generative model
specification language where for time
steps during the time steps of the
simulation there's a
direct distributional
updating
occurring so that's just defines all of
the updates to occur one could imagine
that that that doing the order
differently would matter so maybe it
could be as simple as just these
happening but the the order could matter
and you might not want the order to
matter in exactly the same
um order as the code are
lined but rather to take this um all at
once rep
representation and then further just
from a package perspective it's desired
to have a more of a flexibility with how
you call the statistical distribution so
that again those different Logics can be
hooked up to what is called otherwise if
it's only this expressive and none of
those further steps were taken then this
could just do something as simple as
iterate through in this order but then
to put in logics well like actually do
this one twice as fast or something like
that it would be needing the kind of
rewrite that would result in some of
these
steps
um so technically the agent here goes
through three phases act execute
observe that's one step infer and slide
kind of like act infer surf act execute
observe in this step the agent performs
an action onto the environment at time T
and gets another gets an observation in
exchange these observations are
basically the prediction of the agent on
how the environment evolves over the
next T time
step so act and get an
updated position momentum infer after
receiving observations the agent starts
updating its internal probabilistic
model by doing inference it finds the
posterior distributions over the state
and the control
distributions three slide after updating
its internal belief the agent moves to
the next time step and uses the inferred
action from the previous time step to
interact with the environment and that
is where you pick back up with one so
this is the kind of UDA
toe inactive
Etc and these steps are kind of like
midlevel
functions
um explored on this page here with six
where there's a
future or here it says the O and some of
this might be from an earlier slightly
different version it's just all sort of
directionally uh in the ballpark that
that because the graph doesn't have this
intrinsic scheduling to it then and and
you can have so much flexibility with a
custom scheduling um custom nodes
message rules all that kind of stuff
that um you need to bring how the graph
is called and updated and
operated more explicitly so that's a
good thing it's just that it's still
slightly evolving with many of the
package semantics and examples and norms
and uh there's probably many patterns to
explore and not necessarily some
sequence or repertoire of these
midlevel possibly semantic or or or sub
agentic like steps that give a lot of
nuance with describing is it o o d a or
is it a d o o or is it o o d o o d o o d
Etc okay coming back
to see how simulation okay 52% done on
the meta analysis so that was um that
was the code Vis let's do another code
VI help us
totally understand how the stand
[Music]
alone do mountain
car let's just see if this
works help us totally understand how to
Standalone
Mountain
car script
calls every minute particular and Etc
please thank
you 55%
done reindex
then we'll look we'll see this code Biz
then we'll look at the
um output of the meta analysis okay but
briefly just to look over what they get
to so they Des they describe the
analytical
process formalization for the mountain
so again it's not a proposed reward or
utility function or anything trained on
data it's just a distribution that's
physics grounded using just simply a
gravitational force on the hill
landscape depending on the position and
that's implemented also using possibly
some special characters and some special
Julia syntax that will take some
learning and some package specific
syntax
um so to be leared and and better
understood but here's where they lie out
the functions that create physics and
create world and the sort of world
generative process
element they have a static image just to
confirm that they've initialized
everything here's the naive
approach this is the naive the I think I
have implemented it slightly differently
with just having it all output a one
each time step maybe they're pre-filling
it as
well and then here's the visualization
of just the naive policy having that
initial ramp up then fixed
Point here's the active inference
generative
model okay and
we'll
read now let's help them solve the
problem with an active inference
approach particularly we create an agent
that predicts the future car position as
well as the best possible actions in a
probabilistic manner so not from
data not from data sets we start by
specifying a probabilistic model for the
agent that describes the agent's
internal beliefs over the external
Dynamics over the environment the
generative model is defined as
follows so here are the equations and in
the GitHub
for basically the variables in the base
graph and I I would look forward to um
using some of these new visualization
methods to to
visualize the factors and the app model
from The Notebook visualize the
Standalone and The Meta analysis to
confirm that the um model is being
analyzed correctly okay now let's look
at Standalone well let's just finish
with the what they have in the
documentary here's the
um variables as
defined here's the key RX infer app
model
macro app model maccro and meta blocks
are used to define the probabilistic
model and the approximation methods for
the nonlinear State transition functions
respectively in addition the beliefs
over the future States up to T steps
ahead of the agent is included so this
is like the agent class
equivalent which we looked at briefly
before defined as those distributions
over those
variables after specifying the
generative model let's create an active
inference agent for the car technically
the agent goes through three phases so
here again are those
midlevel sem IC bundles of sort of
distributional updating cognitive sub
agentic process
Etc that are being projected into this
three
cycle act execute
observe in fur slide but that's again as
far as I understood from kis and others
and and learning this year that's just a
convention and other orders or other
kind of um and that could be a good
place to play with this
simulation um and again to confirm
through the flow of the simulation with
the code
viz how the notebook the Standalone and
The Meta analysis
um might be correctly or incorrectly
applied so in So Below we create the
agent through the create agent function
which includes compute act slide and
future so here's future kind of but it
was mentioned
above here is where the reactive message
passing component is
called not exactly
sure what they made about the message so
again just a learning
artifact to try to
understand the the extremely interesting
potential
and directions we can go with the kind
of flexibility that we have with RX and
fur and how cool their Direction and
vision for the open source element is
too so here's the create agents
method now it's time to see
remember now it's time to see if we can
help our friends arrive at the camping
site by midnight question mark
here is
the Julia syntax there's a combination
of initialization methods
parameterization agent
creation further parameter
specification step through experimental
protocol then this discrete time Loop
for the number of time steps as the
active inference simulation's going to
go and then here's a very concise
animation
method and so here it's it's a little
bit different but it's the same kind of
General
picture that is shown here different
scaling colors
um but
that's what is happening in outputs
comparisons
okay and they have more information on
the
um way message passing plays out with
this example okay
all right let's look at the code viz for
the whatever we
prompted okay 83% done with the with the
big meta
analysis okay so here we go here's
Mountain car Standalone 1226
2024 first loads
config
dotel like I don't even know if it
does it
does that's
one it also configures a shared logging
function and a visualization probably
data collect
ction arraying
function so then
these config
informed visualization and
logging
methods are holding the traces of these
two agents as they're simulated within a
shared parameter configuration like
physics and friction that's each cell of
this meta analysis that's ongoing
and each of these agent folders We could
say has like a naive control agent for
that physics combination and a active
influence agent for that physics
configuration the
parameterized sort of
setup for the simulation and everything
loaded in place which can often be a lot
of the the hardest part sometimes cursor
plus llms knocks it out of the park
other times it's it's
um
just two steps backwards one step
forward um Mountain
car is
called interesting
Mountain car.
JL even here looks like it goes to code
of
conduct here's the read me let's look at
that on
GitHub let's look at some of these
methods wow though interesting okay 95%
done with
the um meta
analysis
here's here's the mountain car
model method so here's
Standalone stand alone's parameters are
I I don't know if um terminally I'm sure
it could be restructured
are written at 300 lines in just wanted
to start there to highlight
that so here's how I understand what's
happening in the
Standalone it's defining this as the
mountain car module and and I think a a
better package reference and function
reference could go a long
way here at the package and at the
specific method level RX and fur and
reactive message passing
sub kind of second level Consultants are
called and some of the other packages
that are needed visualization. JL is
brought in for some
methods also this file exports public
functions so other scripts can call
include on this script because and and
get these
functions here are some all right here
we go completed 900 simulations with 80
successes okay good so that that means
that some of the simulations should have
worked some of them didn't work so at
least we picked some interesting area
not sure if it's going to visualize
everything properly
okay here's the app model
function with like the same I
hope um distributions and such here's
the create
physics here's the create
worlds here's the create
agents here's calculating the kinetic
potential and total energy so here's the
the potential
energy with 9.81 gravitational constant
okay no errors from the metaanalysis but
we'll see what it ends up
outputting what was output
so here's the physics-based
energy
calculation not to be confused only to
be distinguished from the fact that
the message passing updates are doing a
free energy minimization but this is
referring to the physics I don't know
what it's if there's a just the physics
phas base
for the Newtonian mechanics
here's the method to call for the
animations that's the module then here
is when
that Standalone is called by itself it
calls in all these other packages here
we're at three line 300 here are the
parameterizations these May
override or or vice
versa and set the shared
parameters for the naive and the active
inference approach here's the act the
naive
approach here's the execution of the
approach this is sort of a procedural
way they defined
um just again like these are this
is like if an example of something that
might be totally Irrelevant in a given
moment or it might make a huge
difference in a simulation so
here they put 100 ones or n naive time
steps of
ones and then just accepted that
Vector here possibly more error prone
possibly introducing um disastrous logic
there's a procedural
generation of setting the action at that
time step to to
one and that enables some of the single
Standalone
logging here's the active inference
approach so it's pre um figured with the
AI namespace
subscript here is
the compute Act slide
future
agents not sure if this 04 gets
overridden we'll see maybe in the meta
analysis here's the active inference
simulation in a let block which helps
with the I I I don't mean
impenetrability security but in the
error tolerance and
logging
for allowances in program so different
sort of footholds entry points for
logging and an understanding and for a
given
situation maybe more or less there's a
lot I I I don't even know so many
different ways to write different
codes so here's the
observation of the position and the
velocity from the current
states modalities factors
here that's the initial
position here is the time step discreete
time sequence so this is kind of like
there's the topos of the the topology of
the action
perception partition and then this is
like the
chyros possibly also Kronos for
specifying how
those different
topological aspects of the action
perception partition get enacted
sequentially in this case but with the
expressivity to have other Logics
underneath
these uh
just current
transient Norm specifications so set the
action to the ACT function push it onto
the action trace and execute the action
then
observe push the observations
store the predictions and and the future
call check against the
target update
beliefs so maybe that's the sort of
running through the Finish Line
component like it checks whether it's
actually at the
goal then it updates its beliefs or but
I'm not sure and logs every 20 time
steps here's the
calculation of the
energies the
visualization on the analysis of the
naive and the
AI comparison plots
outputs some summaries okay so that
again goes to the
outputs folder now let's look at so 17
okay so here's an
anova but here's some earlier ones that
have many more let's try to get these
back first just going to explicitly
bring in
the uh meta analysis and the mountain
car
methods
okay please ensure that all asky art and
non asky parenthesis quote
normal plots
are fly
output by The Meta
analysis then we'll update the toml just
to do a tiny one just to verify
that so we'll do 2 by
two so this is kind of a common sort of
micro Dev Loop
situation with of course just
breaking unworking things but
visualizations sort of trickling off
needing to be
fixed and then the sort of trade-off
between pursuing a local branch and then
pursuing a deeper Branch so for example
here was using the asky text
Art so this was
on 400
50 for
each sweeping so let's see these were
the plain texts we'll see if we can
recover these but you know hilarious if
we can hilarious if we can okay here's
just a sort of summary on the
overall success versus failure of naive
versus active inference so TBD if it's
exactly perfectly doing what the
Standalone does and again if that's
exactly the right or only way way to do
it in the example but at least in this
parameter Zone active inference is doing
better so there's at least some cases
where there's a better policy than just
going to the right success
rates so here's sort of an asky
art
uh visualization not sure if the
dimensionality is right away but it's
sort of it's um
example here's the difference
here's some different plots this is why
it was a local opma because like it
looks kind of sick so I thought okay it
could definitely be also
improved but it's also
like it's cool it can
stay parameter analysis so here's
success rate versus force in the naive
success rate not sure why this wouldn't
be a monotonic
distribution different
plots like plotting this by that
plotting this by
that okay meanwhile I'm going to accept
blindly the edits that it made to the
metaanalysis double check the tomble
we're doing much smaller
situation clear run it again back to the
earlier outputs heat Maps is empty so
that was one of the non asky
art energy
analysis so
this again suggestive that the
simulation really is happening which is
kind of the
question of these
different cases
but it's limited ability with the
aski so
here's
[Music]
um another visualization that's it's
like the control effort distribution by
agent type almost always is at
100 but then there's a few other ones so
not sure if those are
spous or how how those come to be in the
naive control effort case but here is
this um different
distribution okay and Analysis is
empty so here's an example of the sort
of extended startup time of RX
infer okay so this will probably have to
be resolved but here is setting up the
smaller
simulation so it sets up the whole batch
whether it has to do two
or 200,000 and it's going to go a lot
faster it's already at
12%
okay okay so um I'll just sort of read
some of these second uh closing Parts
while we finish up this meta analysis if
you're watching live though write any
comments or questions in the chat okay
so here's some open source to do
um at the package scale just verify and
improve you know anyone who wants to try
can clone the repo get the setup. JL
working on another
setup on the statistical front we could
do better statistical distri description
work visualization and Analysis within
and across simulations
so sort of distinguishing and building
some statistical power apparatus for
technical replicates and biological
replicates or experimental
conditions 19% on the
simulation um on the formal and the
analytical structural side well one
approach is from the initial RX and fer
teams notebook and from the Standalone
and from the uh more meta analysis
style apply uh generalized notation
notation
GNN style which we we we can actually
try
this in in this uh stream
briefly so we'll leave that one up um
category
Theory
here added a couple of links before so
still analyzing The Meta analysis at
least that's a good
sign um so wanted to highlight two
recent blog posts from August and
November of this
year by colleagues at The topos
Institute so the earlier one is a blog
post by Sophie libkin and David SPAC a
polinomial account of basan
update so here they describe this poly
tree notation this is a very math Arty
and
useful uh overview for the Paulie
category theoretic notation and some
operations and probably a ton more for
basian
update and and later they did work
including more of the action side and
then here's a post from uh November of
this year by David
SPAC describing a
paper uh Dynamic task delegation for
hierarchical agents okay met analysis
finished with an
error no look
just fix it thoughtfully
so neural wiring diagrams for message
passing in multiscale organizations
sounds to connect on a lot of ACM topics
so they wrote in our recent paper
Dynamic task delegation for hierarchical
agents Sophie Lipkin deny described a
task delegation from an agent to a team
of subordinates as morphisms in a
certain operad called org
M however such morphisms incl include a
great deal of data and the examples we
gave there barely scratch the surface of
what's possible in this post I'll show
how recumbent neural wiring diagrams
with arbitrary feedback and quote axon
splitting give rise to a message passing
language for describing certain such
task
delegations that is I'll Define a cyclic
operad R
nwd and a function RN WD Arrow
orgm right now what are you doing rnw
ID
and there could be a lot of connections
here with the message passing so I want
to just highlight those see if anyone is
interested
to explore that
direction um just in terms of making
okay
now back to the code here accept the
change
resync it clear start up the meta
analysis
again um on the sort of action
perception Behavioral Science
component fitting
data playing with different noise
patterns and
levels and then also figuring out some
other strategies that can get plugged
in other than the the naive one so just
for reference this is the I believe
formerly known as open AI gym now called
gymnasium do.org so Mountain car here's
how they describe this the environment
is part of the classic control
environments which contains general
information about the
environment so description this is how
they describe it on that gymnasium
situation the mountain car mdp is a
deterministic mdp Markov decision
process that consists of a car placed
stastically at the bottom of a
sinusoidal valley where the only
possible actions being the accelerations
that can be applied to the car in either
direction the goal of the mdp is to
strategically accelerate the car to
reach the goal State on top of the right
Hill there are two versions of a
mountain car domain and gymnasium one
with discrete actions and one with
continuous this version is the one with
discrete actions first appeared in
Andrew Moore's PhD thesis
1990 so here's just how they do so that
that could be cool to bring the RX infer
active inference agent to the gymnasium
and vice
versa another uh angle
here look into the links go to the
multi-agent page in active block FR
project document and and and probably
other and and better um sources for this
too but this is just from from years ago
in the Cyber physical case and the Ant
case some of the different ways that
hopefully RX environments and or similar
will help enable with the expressivity
to talk about a sort of pure blockchain
stigma G Niche
modification
neighborhood where you have a kind of
centralized at that scale of analysis
Hub and spoke to and from like for
example in the blockchain case people
might talk about sending from wallet a
to wallet B but from a message passing
perspective it was wallet a to the
blockchain and then the blockchain
update changes the efficacy at a future
state for B uh whereas the in this case
maybe explicit it's not the best term
here but spatial collisions and direct
interactions are possible as well as
environment interactions so okay we're
back to
the meta
analysis
okay already it looks like more folders
have come
out 16 simulations with four successes
so again some of these should um okay so
here we are within this most
recent we'll wait for this to finish and
then we'll look into this most recent
meta
analysis
okay the heat map
okay
chaos surprise chaos
Mouse over or just copy and paste it
into the
composer
please
thoughtfully address all so that the
visualizations of all kinds are safely
plotted
and fully logged
output okay meanwhile what is happening
in these folders okay heat Maps went
empty but here's what came out before
that okay so here was the smaller
parameterization with these other asy
art
so for the for the cyber Punk solar
Punk RX INF
fur
Enthusiast this one oh is much
bigger the the uh size of the asy art
can be specified in the
tel plot width and plot
height okay meanwhile the agent is
chugging away over
here okay then parameter
analysis with these bigger
ones
so not exactly sure how accurate
everything but okay heat Maps empty
that's kind of part of the
issue okay interesting with a naive
energy
[Music]
distribution asky
plots
nothing
okay accepting these visualization
updates
clear let's just
delete the ones from after 18
call The Meta
analysis it's going to run
it so how can we use RX environments or
Andor others to model this kind of
direct
communication amongst
agents low road or high
road to model transient communication
like propagative radio EMF
light schooling SL
flocking or sort of proximate antenna
antenal
interactions as well as to
model communication through SpaceTime
cones thinking more about topics like
Niche modification stigma G across trial
learning and phermone psychophysics in
the active inference
case Kus live in the
dock okay so here appears to be a key
part of the issue so we'll see how how
much this um interferes with it on this
new run here happening
here but there's some overlap between
the asky
art let's just
preempt ensure that we are not quote
getting it
twisted with the plots
and asky are
art plots math art
plots please check over
everything and fix and trench to
be 100% functionality
okay checking out
the read
me structure of the
repo Standalone implementation physics
engine octave inference agent naive
agent
visualization meta analysis framework at
least the hope of
one
different
measures set up with setup
script run standalone
or The Meta
analysis update Pro config dotl
hopefully project. toml the one with all
the package stuff should be taken care
of by setup but submit a a request or or
let's figure out how to make it
simpler and here are some of those key
packages including RX and
fur okay
all right finished the 16
simulations now it's plotting so we
anything with
18 see but we're already kind
of we're already on
another okay rerunning
it starting now to to fix
but basically this is the whole
coefficient slash question how fast how
good how augmented how clear how well
documented how
aligned how useful how interesting how
novel how
valuable so let's let that simulation go
okay while the meta analysis is
happening let's have just a more
folder let's just see how it does with a
who done
first in who's on
first write
a please write a
comprehensive absolutely
informed and
farsighted slash out
cited
parentheses indoor
outdoor specialist
status who's on
first style
dialogue or
more about
1920s
americ Baseball USA
OS specific lore and all the contents of
the read me and Mountain
car active
inference reactive message passing
scheme as
we've tried to
implement
and dot dot dot
I'll help write a humorous Abbot and
Costello Who's on First style dialogue
that cleverly weaves together classic
baseball references with the mountain
car active inference implementation let
me write this in the who's on first. MD
file 69% done with the
metaanalysis okay
okay let's see
if
okay we'll just do the the the one shot
okay pushed it to
GitHub accept the
changes
clear run at analysis
reload the
repo
more all
right just one shot just so that we can
close
out who's on first Mountain car Edition
say Castello I've been meaning to tell
you about this fascinating new project
we're working on at the Ballpark oh yeah
what's that it's called Mountain car
active inference a mountain car at a
baseball park what are you nuts no no
it's a simulation we've got two agents
trying to get up the hill two agents
like baseball agents no one's active
inference and one's naive well that's
naive of them both who's controlling
them exactly who's controlling the
active agent what's controlling the
naive agent and I don't know is
measuring the performance
metrics wait a minute who's controlling
the active agent yes
precisely I mean the Fell's name who the
agent controlling the car who's
controlling the active inference agent
that's what I'm asking you and I'm
telling you you who is controlling the
active inference agent look let me start
over when you run the simulation who
plots the result oh no who doesn't plot
anything what plots the
results I'm not asking what plots the
results what does plot the results
creates beautiful heat Maps too I don't
care about heat Maps I want to know
who's plotting no no who's controlling
not
plotting then who is plotting
no like I said what plots everything all
right wise guy let me try another way
the car needs to get up the hill right
right so who calculates the force needed
now who only handles active inference I
don't know calculates the forces you
don't know who calculates the
forces no I don't know calculates the
forces that's what I'm asking
you and that's what I'm telling you I
don't know calculates the forces then
who does no who does active inference I
don't know does forces what does
plotting and tomorrow handles the
parameter sweep parameter sweep you
bringing in a grounds keeping now no no
tomorrow is our batch simulation Handler
today is not involved at all how can you
run simulations if today is not
involved why would you want today
involved I'm not asking why oh why is
busy analyzing the energy
consumption I don't even know what we're
talking about anymore that's the spirit
now you're getting it I don't know it's
a crucial part of our
implementation
ah hey wait I haven't told you about
because of statistical significance
testing
yet later that
day okay let me just ask one simple
thing sure in the config file who sets
the initial position oh no naturally
sets the initial position
naturally yes
naturally I should have stayed in the
minor
leagues don't forget practice tomorrow
we're running a full parameter
sweep distance
screaming only to return
to more
airs let's see how far it
got still no heat
Maps Okay um I'll give one more minutes
or so if anybody wants to write a
question in live chat otherwise look
forward to seeing
what people think
um see where it's incorrectly or
inefficiently applying active inference
with RX infer because this is a
really promising direction there's a lot
of interfaces for specifying
simulations making uh versions of the
textbook uh examples
all all kinds of fun research and
education and
application that RX infer is enabling
so I
will accept this last edit make the last
push
yeah composer being able to edit across
multiple
files see this is good it looks good but
it's really hard to see just from a
quick
scan so I'll just leave it at that
close
cursor make
last get push
okay verify that closing edits were sent
all right thank you everyone enjoy I
wish you a good closure of the Year
beginning of the next good
accelerations in this continuous
discreet complex scenario we're in
okay thank you bye